<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" []>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="rfc-tos-specific"
ipr="trust200902" updates="6126">
<front>
<title>TOS-Specific Routing in Babel</title>
<author fullname="Gwendoline Chouasne" initials="G." surname="Chouasne">
<organization>PPS, University of Paris-Diderot</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Case 7014</street>
<city>75205 Paris Cedex 13</city>
<region></region>
<code></code>
<country>France</country>
</postal>
<email>gwendoline.chouasne-guillon@ens.fr</email>
</address>
</author>
<author fullname="Juliusz Chroboczek" initials="J." surname="Chroboczek">
<organization>PPS, University of Paris-Diderot</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Case 7014</street>
<city>75205 Paris Cedex 13</city>
<region></region>
<code></code>
<country>France</country>
</postal>
<email>jch@pps.univ-paris-diderot.fr</email>
</address>
</author>

<date day="10" month="May" year="2017"/>

<abstract>
<t>This document describes an extension to the Babel routing protocol to
support TOS-specific routing. This version is using mandatory sub-TLVs.</t>


</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction and background">

<t>The Type of Service (ToS) or Differentiated Services Code Point (DSCP)
is a field of the IPv4 and IPv6 headers that can be used to request
different per-hop behaviour when forwarding IP packets with identical
source and destination. The most common application of the ToS field is
to request different queueing policies (priority, drop probability, etc.)
from an AQM.</t>

<t>A slightly less common application of the ToS field is to consider it
when performing a routing decision.  A router able to perform ToS-specific
routing maintains a routing table which instead of being merely indexed by
destination prefixes is indexed by pairs of a prefix and a ToS value.  In
order to be routed according to a given entry in the routing table, it
must match not only the destination prefix but also the ToS value.
ToS-specific forwarding is described in more detail in Section ???.</t>

<t>Just like ordinary routes, ToS-specific routes can be installed
manually but are more commonly installed by a dynamic routing protocol.
This document specifies an extension to the Babel routing protocol [BABEL]
that allows it to carry ToS-specific routes.  This extension considers the
ToS field as an opaque value that is only compared for equality, but
ignores the two bits that have been reserved for Explicit Congestion
Notification (ECN) [RFC3168], and is therefore compatible with the
defintion of the ToS field used by DSCP [DSCP].</t>

<t>The extended protocol remains interoperable with the unextended Babel
protocol in a sense made precise in Section ???.</t>

</section>

<section title="Protocol Operation">

<section title="Conceptual Description">

<t>ToS-specific routes are routes that are defined by the same informations
as classic routes, plus a ToS. This protocol handles ToS-specific and
non-ToS-specific routes. Non-ToS-specific routes are treated exactly as
described in the original protocol [BABEL]. ToS-specific routes are also
treated as described in the original protocol [BABEL], with the exception
of the recording of the ToS field in the data structures and the encoding
of Updates and Requests regarding ToS-specific routes. </t>

</section>


<section title="Data Structures">

<t>This extension needs Babel to add a ToS field in the structures it
maintains.</t>

<section title="The Source Table">

<t>The source table maintained by any Babel node, as described in <xref target="BABEL"/>,
Section 3.2.4, needs to be extended with the following field:
<list style="symbols">
<t>the ToS specifying the ToS of packets to which this entry applies.</t>
</list></t>

</section>

<section title="The Table of Pending Requests">

<t>The table of pending requests, maintained by any Babel node, as described in 
<xref target="BABEL"/>, Section 3.2.4, needs to be extended with the following field:
<list style="symbols">
<t>the ToS being requested.</t>
</list></t>
<t>[TODO est-ce que l'indexation a change]?</t>

</section>

</section>

<section title="ToS-specific sub-TLV" anchor="encoding">

<t>This extension defines a new sub-TLV to add a ToS field to a Babel packet.
It turns regular Updates, Route Requests and Seqno Requests into ToS-specific 
Updates, Route Requests and Seqno Requests. Other TLVs SHOULD [TODO ???] NOT use this sub-TLV.</t>

<t>A node MUST send ToS-specific Update, Route Request and Seqno Request if the 
route they advertise is ToS-specific.  Otherwise, a node MUST send non-ToS-specific
Update, Route Request and Seqno Request.</t>

<t>[TODO: supprimer les deux paragraphes suivants]</t>

<t>When a non-ToS-specific Babel node receives an Update, Route Request or Seqno 
Request with a ToS-specific sub-TLV, it will ignore it, according to the base 
protocol defined in <xref target="BABEL"/>.</t>

<t>When a ToS-specific Babel node receives a non-ToS-specific Update, Route Request 
or Seqno Request, it MUST consider this update as a non-ToS-specific Update, Route 
Request or Seqno Request.</t>

<t>The ToS sub-TLV is defined as follow:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2        
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type  = TBD  |    Length     |      ToS      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>Fields :

<list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
<t hangText="Type">Set to TBD to indicate a ToS-specific mandatory sub-TLV..</t>
<t hangText="Length">The length of the body, exclusive of the Type and Length
             fields. It MUST be set to 1.</t>
<t hangText="ToS">The ToS value of the ToS-specific route</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>The value TBD has the mandatory bit set to 1 and this sub-TLV must
therefore be handled in accordance with Section of <xref target="BABEL"/>. [TODO]</t>

</section>

<section title="ToS-specific Messages">

<t>This section describes the handling of ToS-specific messages.</t>

<section title="Updates">

<t>Whenever a ToS-specific Update is sent by a node implementing this extension,
the source table MUST be updated as such : if an entry indexed by
(prefix, plen, router-id, ToS), exists, it MUST be modified as
described in section 3.7.3 of <xref target="BABEL"/>. Otherwise, a new 
entry is created with value (prefix, plen, router-id, ToS, seqno, metric).</t>

</section>

<section title="Requests">

<t>Whenever a node implementing this extension sends a ToS-specific Request,
it MUST add its content as an entry to the Pending Requests Table, as described in section
3.2.6 of <xref target="BABEL"/> [TODO chercher la bonne section], with the suitable ToS.</t>

<section title="Route Requests">

<t> When a node receives a ToS-specific Route Request for a prefix (prefix, plen) and 
a ToS t, it checks its route table for a selected 
route with this prefix, plen, and with ToS t in the corresponding source. If such a route
doesn't exist, it MUST send a ToS-specific retraction for that prefix.</t>

</section>

<section title="Seqno Requests">

<t>When a node receives a Seqno Request for a prefix (prefix, plen) with
a ToS-specific sub-TLV with ToS t, it MUST send a ToS-specific update
with ToS t for a selected route specified by the Plen, Prefix and Source
ToS field, with either a router-id different from what
is specified by the Router-Id field, or a Seqno no less than what is
specified by the Seqno field. If there is no such route in the Route Table,
it MUST forward the seqno request according to the rules defined in Section
3.8.1.2 of <xref target="BABEL"/>. </t>

</section>

</section>

</section>

</section>

<section title="Interaction">

<t>This section describes the interaction of this extension with other protocols
and other versions of Babel.</t>

<section title="ToS interpretation">

<t>Several interpretations have been defined for the ToS field. The ToS field
is opaque to this extension hence, it is compatible with all known and defined
interpretations. In particular, it is compatible with the Differentiated 
Service Field interpretation, defined in RFC 2474, the previous interpretation
described in RFC 791, called IP Precedence, and the ECN protocol, described
in RFC 3168.</t>

</section>

<section title="IP version">

<t>This protocol extension is compatible with IPV4 and IPV6. AE fields 
MUST be filled accordingly, as described in Section 4.1.3 of <xref target="BABEL"/>.</t>

</section>

<section title="Interaction with non-Tos-specific Babel">

<t>The encoding of ToS-specific Updates and Requests is using a reserved sub-TLV. 
This means that, as defined in section ??? of [BABEL], they will be ignored 
by nodes that don't implement this extension, which means that non-ToS-specific nodes
will not treat ToS-specific routes.</t>

<t>In a topology of routers implementing ToS-specific Babel 
and non-ToS-specific Babel, all packets will reach their destination
if it is reachable. Non-ToS-specific packets will follow the same routes 
as if ToS-specific routers were non-ToS-specific routers. ToS-specific packets may
switch to a non-ToS-specific route if and only if there is no route for
the required ToS. </t>

<t>This extension uses a mandatory bit on each sub-TLV. It is necessary 
that this bit is set to 1 for all ToS-specific sub-TLV to avoid loops,
as shown in the following example.</t>

<t>Consider two neighboring routers A and B, A implementing the 
ToS-specific Babel extension, and B implementing just the base Babel 
protocol. Suppose that A has a ToS-specific route for a prefix P and ToS t.</t>
<t>B will receive an update from A with this ToS-specific route. Suppose that
B reads the update TLV but drops the ToS-specific sub-TLV. It will now
forwards packets for P through A.</t>
<t>B will then send an update for the route to (P) to A. A will take B as next-hop
for the matching packets.</t>
<t>When a packet with ToS t arrives to A or B, it will travel between A and B 
indefinitely, as shown in the figure below.</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
             (P)            (P)
             -->            <--
----------- A ----------------- B -----------
        <--
      (P, t)
]]></artwork></figure>


</section>

<section title="Interaction with other known extensions">

<t>[TODO : a ecrire, mais a definir avant]</t>

</section>

<section title="Lower Layer">

<t>When a packet for an address A arrives to a node, it may match several routes,
and the node MUST choose the most specific one.</t>

<t>However, one needs to define what is the most specific route between
one with a prefix including A but no ToS, and one with a 
less specific prefix, and the ToS required by the packet.</t>

<t>It is necessary that all routers use the same priority rules between 
destination and ToS to avoid creating routing loops.</t>

<t>A Babel implementation with this extension MUST choose the route with the 
destination-first ordering. This ordering first considers the routes with
the most specific prefixes, and then chooses among them the one with the
ToS of the packet. If it doesn't exist, then it gradually considers the
routes with the less specific prefixes, until it finds one with the required
ToS. </t>

<t>This means that a Babel implementation of this extension must ensure that
lower layers observe these semantics. If they don't, 
the implementation MUST disambiguate the routing tables by using a suitable
algorithm (for example the algorithm of M. Boutier <xref target="SS-ROUTING"/>).</t>

</section>

</section>

<section title="todos">

<t>Compression</t>
<t>Wildcard requests</t>

</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">

<t>IANA is instructed to add the following entry to the "Babel sub-TLV type"
registry:</t>

<texttable>
<ttcol>Type</ttcol><ttcol>Name</ttcol><ttcol>Reference</ttcol>
<c>TBD</c><c>ToS-specific TLV</c><c>(this document)</c>
</texttable>

</section>

<section title="Security considerations">

<t>The extension defined in this protocol defines three new sub-TLVs for
defined TLVs. This extension doesn't alterate any of the security properties
of the base protocol.</t>

</section>

</middle>

<back>

<references title="Normative References">

<reference anchor="BABEL">
   <front>
      <title>The Babel Routing Protocol</title>
      <author initials="J" surname="Chroboczek" fullname="Juliusz Chroboczek"><organization/></author>
      <date month="July" day="8" year="2016"/>
   </front>
   <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-chroboczek-babel-rfc6126bis-00"/>
   <format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-chroboczek-babel-rfc6126bis-00.txt"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="BABEL-EXT"><front>
<title>Extension Mechanism for the Babel Routing Protocol</title>
<author fullname="Juliusz Chroboczek" initials="J." surname="Chroboczek"/>
<date day="28" month="May" year="2015"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7557"/>
</reference>

</references>

<references title="Informative References">

<reference anchor="SS-ROUTING">
<front>
<title>Source-Specific Routing</title>
<author initials="M." surname="Boutier" fullname="Matthieu Boutier"/>
<author initials="J." surname="Chroboczek" fullname="Juliusz Chroboczek"/>
<date year="2014" month="August"/>
</front>
<annotation>In Proc. IFIP Networking 2015.  A slightly earlier version
is available online from http://arxiv.org/pdf/1403.0445.</annotation>
</reference>

<reference anchor="TOS-ROUTING">
<front>
<title>ToS-Specific Routing</title>
<author initials="M." surname="Boutier" fullname="Matthieu Boutier"/>
<author initials="J." surname="Chroboczek" fullname="Juliusz Chroboczek"/>
<date year="2014" month="August"/>
</front>
<annotation>[TODO mettre un bo article qui parle de ToS]</annotation>
</reference>

</references>

</back>

</rfc>
